foreign
but it doesn't really matter how you
translate it well
it doesn't matter as much as how you
contemplate it
so how would you contemplate cessation
how would you contemplate need order
on a day-to-day practical basis
what would that contemplation entail are the
ways in which I'm acting
that by body or by speech or by mind
so say say you're not you're restrained
you're not acting out you're not
perpetuating the ownership
so how would you then go about
contemplating your order
in Aggregates and feelings
deceptions intentions consciousness what
what
what actual property
what actual quality would you be
reflecting upon if you're contemplating
near order of the Aggregates what is it
contemplating their disappearance that's
kind of inconceivable like while you're
alive while you're paired with you know
while these Aggregates are composed the
way they are you couldn't even conceive
them not being there because you thought
of their cessation is within the
existing Aggregates so it's not about
Aggregates disappearing from your
experience it's not about your feelings not arising
it's not about your feelings not arising
or your perceptions never coming back
again and intentions just going numb
so it's not about that because it's
inconceivable so what is it about then
to see that they have risen on their own
like okay they have come but they were
there and then what could be the quality
of that
say you're currently enduring feeling or
perception or your state of mind so what
would be the quality what would be the
quality of um
neroda in those things what would be the
quality of that uh
that Arisen on its own unable
yeah so it's not about cessation it's
not about disappearance it's not about
this perception should disappear for me
in order to understand it will be free
from it
by the opposite freedom from besetting
perceptions freedom from painful feelings freedom
freedom from painful feelings freedom
from pressures is while those things are
present so then when the when the neurodes
so then when the when the neurodes
translated cessation
that cessation does well should not be
understood in a sense of these things
just not being there anymore
not being The Disappearance what is it
then disappearance of ownership abandonment
disappearance of ownership abandonment
the spirit of ownership yeah you could
say that because that thing would still
remain but you would not own it yeah
hey so so yeah like you say
so then would you say that contemplation
contemplating neroda in aggregates is
contemplating non-ownership of the
aggregates yeah yeah you could say that way yeah
yeah yeah you could say that way yeah
exactly
um and the other way you could
contemplate those aspects
they would contribute towards the
contemplation of non-ownership
that would be
um
contemplating rightly along the lines of
miroda along the lines of cessation
along the lines of cessation
along the lines of unknown ability
because it kind of boils down to that
you can't own it
like your own feelings your own moods
your own perceptions
even if you want to but the only way to
like like thoroughly understand
the extent of that known ownership you
have to allow that thing to arise
to its full extent to whatever extent
extent it wants to arise you must not be
interfering with its arising and that's
why the sultan is understanding is
whatever has the nature of arising
that's why it's niroda basically that's
why it has a nature to cease I to be
unable to be seen as is completely
um
pretty much
impossible to own
in any shape or form while it's there
so then the mirror arising of things the
mirror rising of the feelings of your
intentions of your perceptions
is then
uh showing you its own unknown ability
basically the mirror Rising then starts
equaling freedom from it
if you allow it to the extent
if you allow it to rise to the extent he
wants to rise to that extent you'll be
free from it
to that extent you will not be hindered
obstructed by it to that extent you will
not take up the ownership
but kind of seeing Rising as a reasoning
Zone yeah when I say arising means
manifestation means enduring means
finding it there means coming into being
intensifying fading in doesn't matter
how you want to describe it doesn't mean
like in the same senses neroda does not
mean the ending
arising does not mean you see it
beginning before which it was not
okay [Music]
[Music]
because yeah if you're if you're
observing something that it was not and
now it just appeared that's not on the
right level where the five Aggregates
are that's too particular that's just
something secondary within your sense
base is that you are just measuring like
scientists and so on
no no we're talking about on the level
of the experience as a whole
so you as a as an observing individual
are not
absorbed in observation
but actually emphasis is on the uh
self-reflection of the experience of
observation or whatever else you might
be doing
on that level you find things already
being there pressuring you being felt
being intended being perceived
so recognizing their
manifested enduring there
without acting out obviously to the
extent that it's manifested
to that extent you become free
because no extent can be owned
but the reason you never get to
understand that fully is because you
interfere with the extent of arising
because if it's Pleasant
you cut it short by wanting more of it
if it's unpleasant you cut the chore by
trying to get rid of it if it's neutral
you cut it short By ignoring it
and you don't actually get to see the
obvious which is whatever has the nature
of horizon has an age disease for their
very reason has the nature to not hinder
you as the nature to not be owned as the
nature to being permanent
has the nature of change
but like we said there are many times
it's it's a vicious circle
it's a vicious circle
without the beginning as well because
you act because you are affected by it
and then
through acting you yeah that's from your
ownership the right instruction has to
come from the outside somebody who has
understood this has to tell you and you
have to take it out of Faith initially
just so that you stop acting out and
cutting it short
that's the point
and by the way there are many like
um
day-to-day examples of how you you would
cut short these mental States
psychologization would be one of them
explaining things because they bother
you so you know so you get some
resolution you want to deal with those
things on that level mental level to
clarify it to free yourself from doubt
through finding answers and all of that
all that's rooted in in cutting the
unpleasant feeling short
or somebody says Oh see now all this
thinking this is causing you suffering
so stop thinking just observe Sensations
watch the nostrils
uh and and do not allow thoughts
basically to arise well that's another
way of cutting things short
you again you don't want to deal with it
so one way you want to deal with it too
much this way you don't want to deal
with it at all but if it has a reason to
the extent it has arisen to that extent
you have to do it because that's the
only way
to fully kind of
um
hammer in the fact that it's unownable
but you might be telling yourself that
it's unable as much as you want but when
plus unpleasant feeling manifests itself
when something that bothers you comes up
and you just want to resolve it deal
with it ignore it turn away from it
meditate away from it means you took the
ownership of it that's why you're acting
out because if it's unable what is there to
because if it's unable what is there to
resolve if it's not yours
it's not your problem why is there to to
be bothered about and deal with it and
fight over and
that's the difference between Theory and
the practice really like everybody can
read in each and can say oh this isn't
it but do you when they're pressuring
things manifest do you do you allow them
to arise to the extent they want to
arise do you are you able to remain
composed in your samadhi without acting
out of them
for as long as they last or not
that's the measure of whether you are
actually seeing that neroda correctly or
not or you're getting closer to see it
correctly or not
whether you're
um
extinguishing the ownership or fueling
it
through acting up
could another way of describing this
contemplation be
that it's not it's never
in in the content of
um
you know I I'm Pleasant
experiences or or Pleasant experiences
or neutral experiences
um
but it's always the attitude towards
those feelings or those yeah experiences
in the broadest sense
but the reason why that would for most
people especially in the beginning there might
especially in the beginning there might
be just too abstract for them
like when you say feeling in the broader
sense it just becomes an abstract
category that they cannot relate to is
because the the body and the actions
have not been purified and the mind have
not been has not been withdrawn from
unwholesome States through sensory
strained in other words you're still operating on
in other words you're still operating on
the level of content of your senses
pleasing content displeasing content you
know prolong avoid gain more
so the share kind of broadness of the
category of feeling in that broader
sense of a of a mood Pleasant unpleasant
neutral that's just too far to be seen
so it just is just an abstract thought
that has no practical elements because
the mind has not been elevated to that
level and you elevate it not through a special
and you elevate it not through a special
practice or a magical method or
something you elevated through saying no
to your desires
and you're gonna start going up which is
why you know people get scared